Welcome to this free online class on Machine Learning.
Machine Learning is one of
the most exciting recent technologies and
in this class, you learn about
the state of the art and also
gain practice implementing at the point these algorithms yourself.
You probably used a learning
algorithm dozens of times a day without knowing it.
Every time you use a web
search engine, like Google or Bing to search the internet.
One of the reasons that it works so
well is because a learning
algorithm when implemented by
Google or Microsoft has learned how to rank what pages.
Every time you use Facebook or
Apple's photo tagging application and
it recognizes your friend's photos,
that's also Machine Learning.
Every time you read your email and your spam
filter saves you from having
to wade through tons of spam email.
That's also a learning algorithm.
For me, one of the
reasons I am excited is
the AI dream of some
day building machines as intelligent
as you are.
We are a long way away from that goal.
But many AI researchers believe that
the best way towards that goal
is through learning algorithms. They try
to mimic how the human brain
learns.
I'll tell you a little bit about that too in this class.
In this class, you learn about state-of-the-art machine learning algorithms.
But it turns out, just knowing
the algorithms and knowing the math is not that much good.
If you don't also know how
to actually get this stuff to
work on problems that you care about.
So we have also spent a lot of time developing exercises
for you to implement each of these
algorithms and see how they work with yourself.
So why is machine learning so prevalent today?
It turns out that Machine Learning
is a few that have grown
out of field of AI or Artificial Intelligence.
We wanted to build intelligent machines
and it turns out that there
are a few basic thing we could program
a machine to do such as
how to find the shortest path
from A to B.  But for
the most part, we just did
not know how to write
AI programs to do the
more interesting things such as
web search or photo tagging or email anti-spam.
There is a realization that
the only way to do these
things was to have a machine learn to do it by yourself.
So, Machine Learning was
developed as a new capability for computers.
And today it touches many
segments of industry and basic science.
For me, I work on
Machine Learning and in a
typical week, I might end
up talking to helicopter
pilots, biologists, a bunch of
computer systems people and so are like my colleagues here at Stanford.
And averaging two or three
times a week, I would get
email from people in industry, from
Silicon Valley, contacting me
who have an interest in applying
learning algorithms to their own problems.
This is a sign of the
range of problems that Machine Learning
touches: the isotonic bodies,
composition biology, tons of
things of Silicon Valley that
Machine Learning is having an
impact on.
Here are some modern examples of Machine Learning.
There's database mining.
One of the reasons Machine Learning
is so prevalent is the growth of the web and the growth of automation.
All this means that we have much larger data assessment then ever before.
So, for example, tons of
Silicon Valley companies are today
collecting web click data, also
called click stream data, and I'm
trying to use Machine Learning algorithms
to mine this data to understand
the users better and to serve the users better.
There's a huge segment of Silicon Valley right now.
Medical records, with the
advent of automation, we now
have electronic medical records so
if we can turn medical records
into medical knowledge, then we
can start understand disease better.
Computational biology. We've automationally gained.
Biologists are collecting once
the data about gene sequences,
DNA sequences and so on.
And Machine Learning algorithms are giving
us a much better understanding of
the human genome and what
it means to be human, and in engineering as well.
In all fields of engineering we
have larger and larger, larger and
larger data sets that we're trying to understanding using learning algorithms.
A second range of
Machine Learning applications is ones
that we can not program by hand.
So, for example, I've worked on
autonomous helicopters for many years.
We just did not know how to
write a computer program to make this helicopter fly by itself.
The only thing that worked was
how the computer learn by
itself how to fly
this helicopter.
Handwriting recognition.
It turns out, one of the
reasons it's so inexpensive today
to route a piece of mail
across the country in the
US and internationally is that
when you write an envelope like
this, it turns out there's
is a learning algorithm that has
learned how to read your handwriting
so that it can automatically route this envelope on its way.
So it costs us
a few cents to send this thing thousands of miles.
And in fact, if you've seen the fields of
natural language processing or
computer vision, you saw
the use of AI pertaining
to understanding language or understanding images.
Most of natural language processing, most
of computer vision today is applied to machine learning.
Learning algorithms are also widely used for self-customizing programs.
Every time you go to Amazon
or Netflix or iTunes Genius and
it recommends movies or products
of music to you that's a learning algorithm.
If you think about it'd have a million users.
There is no way to write a
million different programs for the million users.
The only way to have
software get these customized recommendations
is if it can learn by itself
to customize itself to your preferences.
Finally, learning algorithms are being
used today to understand
human learning and to understand the brain.
We'll talk about how researchers are
using this to make progress
towards the big eon dream.
A few months ago, a student
showed me an article on the top 12 IT skills.
The skills that information technology hiring
managers cannot say no to.
It's a slightly older article, but at
the top of this list
of the 12 most desirable IT skills
was the machine learning.
Here at Stanford, the number
of recruiters that contact me
asking if I know any graduating
e-learning students is far
larger than the number of
Machine Learning students that we gradually hear.
So I think there's a vast unfulfilled
demand for the skill set, and this
is a great time to be
learning about Machine Learning and I
hope to teach you a lot about Machine Learning in this class.
In the next video we'll start
to give a formal definition of
what is Machine Learning and we'll
begin to talk about the main
types of Machine Learning problems and algorithms. You
pick up some of the main
Machine Learning terminology and start
to get a sense of what
are the different algorithms and when each one might be appropriate.