What is Machine Learning?
In this video we will try
to define what it is and
also try to give you
a sense of when you want to use Machine Learning.
Even among machine learning practitioners
there isn't a well accepted
definition of what is and what isn't Machine Learning.
But let me show you a couple
of examples of the ways
that people have tried to define
it.
Here is the definition of what is
Machine Learning does do to Arthur Samuel.
He defined Machine Learning as the
field of study that gives computers
the ability to learn without being explicitly programmed.
Samuel's claim to fame was
that back in the 1950's, he wrote a checkers playing program.
And the amazing thing about
this checkers playing program was
that Arthur Samuel himself wasn't a very good checkers player.
Well, what he did was
he had to program play tens
of thousands of games against itself.
And by watching what sorts of
board positions tended to lead
to wins and what sort
of board positions tended to lead to losses.
The checkers playing program learned
over time what are good
board positions and what are
bad board positions, and eventually
learned to play checkers better than Arthur
Samuel himself was able to.
This was a remarkable result.
Arthur Samuel himself turned out
not to be a very good
checkers player, but because
a computer has the patience
to play tens of thousands of games against itself.
No human has the patience to play that many games.
By doing this, the computer was
able to get so
much checkers playing experience that
it eventually became a better
checkers player than Arthur Samuel himself.
This is somewhat informal
definition and an older one.
Here's a slightly more recent definition
by Tom Mitchell who's a friend of Carnegie Mellon.
So, Tom defines Machine
Learning by saying that, a
well opposed learning problem is
defined as follows, he says,
a computer program is said
to learn from experience E with respect to
some task T and some performance
measure P. And if this performance
on T as measured by P
improves some experience E. I
actually think he came up with this definition just to make it rhyme.
Well the checkers-playing example is:
the experience E would
be the experience of having
the program play tens of
thousands of games against itself.
The Task T would be
the task of playing checkers
and the performance measure P would
be the probability that it
wins the next game of checkers against some new opponent.
Throughout these videos, besides me
trying to teach you stuff, I'll
occasionally ask you a
question to make sure you understand the content.
Here's one.
On top is a definition of
"Machine Learning" by Tom Mitchell.
Let's say your email program watches
which emails you do or do not tag as spam.
So, in an email plan
like this, you might click the
spam button to report
some email as spam but
not all the emails, and
based on which emails you mark as spam.
Say your email program learns
better how to filter spam email.
What is the task T in this setting?
In a few seconds, the video
will pause and when it
does so, you can use
your mouse to select one of
these four radio buttons to
let, to let me know
which of these four you think
is the right answer to this question.
So hopefully you got that
this is the right answer, because find emails is a task T.
In fact, this definition defines
a task T, a performance measure
P, and this experience
E. And so watching
you label emails, as spam
or not spam, this would be
the experience E, and the
fraction of emails correctly classified
that might be a performance
measure P. And so
our task performance, on the
task about systems performance, on
the task T, on the
perform measure P will improve
after the experience E. In
this class I hope to teach
you about various different types of learning algorithms.
There are several different types of learning algorithms.
The main two types are what
we call Supervised Learning and Unsupervised Learning.
I'll define what these terms mean more in the next couple of videos.
But it turns out that in
Supervised Learning, the idea
is we're going to teach the computer
how to do something, whereas
in Unsupervised Learning, we're going to let it learn by itself.
Don't worry if these two terms don't make sense yet.
In the next two videos, I'm
going to say exactly what these two types of learning are.
You might also hear
other buzz terms such as
"Reinforcement Learning" and "Recommender Systems".
These are other types of Machine Learning algorithms that we'll talk about later.
But the two most
used types of learning algorithms
are probably Supervised Learning and
Unsupervised Learning and Define
them in the next two videos
and we'll spend most this class talking about these two types of learning algorithms.
It turns out one of the
other things we'll spend a lot
of time on in this class is
practical advice for applying learning algorithms.
This is something that I feel
pretty strongly about and it's
actually something that I don't know
if any other university teaches.
Teaching about learning algorithms
is like giving a set of
tools, and equally important
or more important than giving
you the tools is to teach you how to apply these tools.
I like to make an analogy to learning to become a carpenter.
Imagine that someone is teaching
you how to be a carpenter, and
they say here's a hammer,
here's a screwdriver, here's a saw, good luck.
Well that's no good, right?
You have all these tools
but the more important thing, is
to learn how to use these tools properly.
There's a huge difference between people
that know how to use these
Machine Learning algorithms versus people
that don't know how to use these tools well.
Here in Silicon Valley where
I live, when I
go visit different companies, even
the top Silicon Valley companies,
very often I see people
trying to apply Machine Learning
algorithms to some problem, and
sometimes they'll have been going
at it for six months, but sometimes
when they look at what they're doing,
I say, you know, I could
of told them like "Gee, I
could of told you six months
ago that you should
be taking a learning algorithm and
applying it in like the
slightly modified way and
your chance of success would have been much higher."
So what we're gonna
do in this class is actually
spend a lot of time talking
about how, if you're actually
trying to develop a Machine
Learning system, how to
make those best practices type
decisions, about the way
in which you build your system, so
that when you're applying learning algorithm, you
are less likely to end up
one of those people who end
up pursuing some path for
six months that you know,
someone else could have figured
out just wasn't gonna work at all and was just a waste of time for six months.
So I'm actually gonna spend
a lot of time teaching you those sorts
of best practices and Machine Learning
and AI, and how to get those stuff to work.
And how we do it and
how the best people do it, is Silicon Valley and around the world.
I hope to make you one of
the best people at knowing how
to design and build serious
Machine Learning and AI systems.
So that's Machine Learning and
these are the main topics I hope to teach.
In the next video I'm going
to define what is
Supervised Learning and after
that what is Unsupervised Learning and
also, we'll start to talk
about when you would use each of them.