In this video, I'm going to
define what is probably the
most common type of machine
learning problem, which is Supervised Learning.
I'll define Supervised Learning more
formally later, but it's probably
best to explain, or start
with an example of what it
is and we'll do the formal definition later.
Let's say you want to predict housing prices.
A while back, a student
collected data sets from
the city of Portland, Oregon,
and let's say you plot
the data set and it looks like this.
Here on the horizontal axis, the
size of different houses in square
feet, and on the vertical
axis the prices of
different houses in thousands of dollars.
So, given this data,
let's say you have a friend
who owns a house
that is, say, 750 square
feet and they're hoping
to sell the house and they
want to know how much they can get for the house.
So how can a learning algorithm help you?
One thing a learning algorithm might
be able to do is put a straight line through the data.
So I'll fit a straight line to
the data and based
on that, it looks like
maybe the house can be
sold for maybe about $150,000.
But maybe this isn't the
only learning algorithm you can
use and there might be a better one.
For example, instead of fitting
a straight line to the data,
we might decide that it's better
to fit a quadratic function or
a second order polynomial to this
data, and if you
do that and make a
prediction here, then it
looks like, well, maybe they
can sell the house for
closer to $200,000.
One of the things
we'll talk about later is how
to choose and how to decide,
do you want to fit a
straight line to the data, or
do you want fit the quadratic function to the data?
And it is no fair picking
whichever one gives your friend the better house to sell.
But each of these would be a fine example of a learning algorithm.
So, this is an
example of a Supervised Learning algorithm.
And the term "Supervised Learning" refers
to the fact that we gave
the algorithm a data set
in which the  "right answers" were given.
That is, we gave it
a data set of houses in
which for every example in
this data set, we told
it what is the right
price or what was the actual
price that that house sold for.
And the task of
the algorithm was to just
produce more of these right
answers, such as for
this new house you know, that your friend may be trying to sell.
To define the terminology, this
is also called a regression problem.
And by regression problem, I
mean we're trying to predict a
continuous value output, namely the price.
So technically, I guess, prices can
be rounded off to the nearest
cent, so maybe prices are actually discrete value.
But usually we think of the
price of a house as a real number or
as a scale of value, as a continuous value number.
And the term regression refers to
the fact that we are trying
to predict this sort of continuous values attribute.
Here is another Supervised Learning example.
Some friends and I actually worked on this earlier.
Let's say you want to look
at medical records and try
to predict that a breast cancer
is malignant or benign.
If someone discovers a breast
tumor, a lump in their
breast, a malignant tumor
is a tumor that is
harmful and dangerous, and
a benign tumor is a tumor that's harmless.
So, obviously people care a lot about this.
Let's say you collect a data set
and suppose in your data
set you have, on your
horizontal axis the size
of the tumor, and on the
vertical axis, I'm going
to plot one or zero,
yes or no, whether or not
these are examples of tumors
we've seen before are malignant just
one or zero, or not malignant or benign.
So let's say your data
set looks like this where we
saw a tumor of this size that turned out to be benign.
One of this size, one of
this size, and so on.
And sadly, we also saw a few malignant tumors.
So one of that size, one
of that size, one of
that size, so on.
So this example I have five
examples of benign tumors
shown down here, and five
examples of malignant tumors
shown with a vertical axis value of one.
And let's name a friend
who tragically has a breast
tumor and let's say
her breast tumor size is
maybe somewhere around this value.
The machine learning question is: can
you estimate what is the
probability, what is the
chance that a tumor is malignant versus benign?
To introduce a bit more
terminology this is an
example of a classification
problem.
The term classification refers to
the fact that here we are
trying to predict a discrete value
output, zero or one,
malignant or benign.
And it turns out that
in classification problems sometimes you
can have more than two values
for the, two possible values for the output.
As a complete example maybe there
are three types of breast cancers
and so you may try
is predicted this be value of 0, 1, 2, or 3.
Where 0 may mean benign,
benign tumor so no
cancer and 1 may
mean type 1 cancer.
I guess three types of cancer
whether the type one means and
two may mean the second type
of cancer and three may
mean the third type of cancer,
but this would also be a
classification problem because, so
the despite value set
of outputs, because only to
no cancer or cancer type
one, or cancer type two, or cancer type three.
In complication problem, there 's
just another way to plot this data.
Let me show you what I mean.
We're going to use a slightly different set of symbols to plot this data.
So if tumor size is
going to be the attribute that
I'm going to use to predict malignancy
or benignness, I can also draw my data like this.
I'm going to use different
symbols to denote my benign
and malignant or my negative and positive examples.
So, instead of drawing crosses, I
am now going to draws o's
for the benign tumors.
Like so.
And I'm great to keep using
x's to denote my
malignant tumors.
Okay?
I hope this makes sense.
All I did was I took,
you know, these, my data set
on top and I just mapped
it down to this
real line like so and
started to use different symbols,
circles and crosses, to denote
malignant versus benign examples.
Now in this example,
we use only one feature or
one attribute, namely, the
tumor size, in order to
predict whether tumor is malignant or benign.
In other machine learning problems when
we have more than one feature,
more than one attribute. Here's an example.
Let's say that instead of
just knowing the tumor size, we
know both the age of the
patient and the tumor size.
In that case, maybe your data
set would look like this,
where I may have a
set of patients With those
edges and that tumor size,
they look like this, and difference
of the patients that look
a little different, whose tumors
turn out out to be malignant
as denoted by the causes.
So, let's say you have a
friend who tragically has a
tumor, and maybe their
tumor size and edge falls around there.
So, given a data set like
this, what the learning algorithm
may do is build a
straight line to the data
to try to separate
out the malignant tumors from
the benign ones, and so
the learning algorithm may decide
to build a straight line
that to separate out the two
causes of tumors and, you
know, with this, hopefully we can
decide that your friend's tumor
is more likely, if it's
over there, that hopefully the
learning algorithm will say that your
friends tumor falls on this
benign side and is
therefore more likely to be
benign than xx in this
example we had two features,
namely the age of the
patient and the size
of the tumor in other
machines reporting problems, we
will often have more features
and my friends that work on
this problem they actually use other
features like this which is
clump thickness, clump thickness of the breast tumor.
Uniformity to the cell
size of the tumor, uniformity of
the cell shape of the tumor
and so on and other features as well.
And it turns out one
of the most interesting learning algorithms
that we will see in this pass is
a learning algorithm that can deal
with not just two
or three or five features,
but an infinite number of features.
On this slide are listed
a total of five different features,
right; two on the axis and three more up here.
It turns out for some learning
problems what you really want
is not to use like three
or five features, but instead you
want to use an infinite number
of features an infinite number
of attributes, so that your
learning algorithm has lots of
attributes or features to use
with which to make our predictions.
So, how do you deal with an infinite number of features?
And so how do you
restore an infinite number of things on a computer?
Your computer runs on a memory.
As it turns out that when
we talk about an algorithm called the support vector
machine, there will be a
need to mathematically trick that
will allow a computer to
deal with an infinite number of features.
Imagine that I did just write down, you know, two features here.
I think it's 3 features on the right.
But imagine that I wrote
down a infinitely long list,
I just kept writing more and more and more features.
Like an infinitely long list of features.
Turns out we'll give it that come with an algorithm taken to your order.
So, just a recap. In
this class, we'll talk about Supervised
Learning and the idea
is that, in Supervised Learning
in every example in our
data set we are told
what is the "correct answer"
that we would have quite liked
the algorithms to predict a
better example, such as
the price of the house or whether
a tumor is malignant or benign.
We also talked about the
regression problem and by
regression, that means that
our goal is to predict a
continuous valued output, and
we talked about the classification
problem where the goal
is to predict a discrete
value output.
Give us a quick wrap up question.
Suppose you're running a company and
you want to develop learning algorithms
to address each of two problems.
In the first problem you have
a large inventory of identical items.
So imagine that you have
thousands of copies of some
identical items to sell, and
you want to predict how many
of these items you sell over the next three months.
In the second
problem, problem two, you
have lots of users and
you want to write software to
examine each individual of
your customer's accounts, each one
of your customer's accounts, and for
each account, decide whether or
not the account has been hacked or compromised.
So for each of these problems,
should they be treated as a
classification problem, or as
a regression problem?
When the video pauses, please
use your mouse to select whichever
of these four options on
the left you think is the correct answer.
So hopefully you got that this is the answer.
For problem one, I would
treat this as a regression
problem because if I have,
you know, thousands of items, well
I would probably just treat this
as a real value, as a
continuous value, and treat
therefore the number of
items I sell as a continuous value.
And for the second problem, I
would treat that as a classification
problem because I might
say set the value
I want to predict, to be
zero to denote the
account has not been hacked,
and set the value one to
denote an account that has been hacked into.
So just like, you know, breast
cancer is right, zero is benign,
one is malignant, so I might
set, this be 0 or
1 depending on whether it's been
hacked and have an algorithm
try to predict each one
of these two discreet values, and
because there's a small number
of discreet values I would
therefore treat it as a classification problem.
So, that's it for
Supervised Learning and in
the next video, I'll talk about
Unsupervised Learning, which is
the other major category of learning algorithm.