Our first learning algorithm will be linear regression.
In this video, you see what
the model looks like and more
importantly, you also see
what the overall process of Supervised Learning looks like.
Let's use some motivating examples of predicting housing prices.
We're going to use a data
set of housing prices from
the city of Portland, Oregon.
And you're going to plot
my data set of a
number of houses that were
of different sizes that were
sold for a range of different prices.
Let's say that given this data
set you have a friend that's
trying to sell a house and
let's see, your friend's house is
of size 1250 square feet,
and you want to tell them
how much they might be able to sell the house for.
Well, one thing you could do
is fit a model,
maybe you put a straight line
to this data, something like
that, and based on that,
maybe you can tell your friend that,
it looks like he can maybe sell the
house for around to a $1000.
So, this is an
example of a Supervised
Learning algorithm and it's
Supervised Learning because we've given
the right answer for each
of our examples, namely we're
told what was the actual holes.
What was the actual prices for each of the houses, you know, data server.
And moreover, just an
example of a regression problem where
the term regression at first
the back that we're predicting the
raw value of what, maybe
the price and just to
remind you, the other
most common type of Supervised Learning
problem is called is
classification problem where we
predict discrete value outputs.
Such as if we are
looking at cancer tumors and
trying to decide if the tumor
is malignant or benign.
So, that's a 0-1 value.
Well, formally, in Supervised Learning,
we have a data set and
this data set is called a training set.
So, for housing prices example for
wherever training sets of different
housing prices and our
job is to learn from
this data how to predict the prices of the houses.
Let's define some notation that we're using throughout this course.
We're going to find quite a lot of symbols.
It's OK if you don't
remember all the symbols right now,
but as the course progresses, they'll
useful if you need notation.
I'm going to use lowercase "m" throughout
this course to denote the number of training examples.
So, in this data set, if
I have, let's say
47 rows in this table,
then I have 47 training examples
and m equals 47.
Then I use lowercase
x to denote the input
variables often also called the purchase.
So, that would be x's here,
with the ID of the
purchase and I'm going to use
y to denote my on-point
variables, or the target
variable that I'm trying to predict.
So that's this second column here.
On notation, I'm going to
use x y
to denote a single training example.
So, a single row in
this table corresponds to the
single training example and to
refer to a specific training
example, I'm going to
use this notation xi, yi
and I'm going
to use this to refer to
the i training example.
So this superscript i over
here, this is
not exponentiation, right, this
x(i), y(i), the superscript i
in parentheses, that's just
an index into my training
set and that refers to the i-th row of this table.
Okay?
So, this is not x to
the power of i, y to the
power of i. Instead x(i), y(i)
just refers to the
i row of this table.
So for example, x1 refers to.
If a value for our first
three examples, so this
2, 1, or 4, that gives us x in the first row.
x will be equal
to 1460 -
that's the second X
- and my 1 will be equal to well, 60 because that's
the first, the y value with my first training example.
I guess with that one.
The first two.
So, as I mentioned, occasionally, I'll
ask you a question, to let
you check your own standing, in
a few seconds in this video,
a multiple choice question will pop up in the video.
When it does, please use your
mouse to select what you think is the right answer.
We'll define what the training set
is, and so here's what we supervise learning and how he works.
We saw them with a training
set like our training sets of
housing prices and we feed
that to our learning algorithm.
It is the job of the learning
algorithm to then output
the function which by convention
is usually denoted lower case
h, and h stands for hypothesis.
And what the job of the
hypothesis is, is a
function that takes it's
input the size of
a house like maybe the size
of a new house that you know
your friend's trying to sell,
so assuming the value of
x, and it try
to output the estimated
value of Y
for their corresponding house.
So h is a function
that maps from x's
to y's.
People often ask me, you know, "Why is this function called hypothesis?"
Some of you may know the meaning
of the term "hypothesis" from the dictionary of science, or whatever.
It turns out that in machine
learning, this was a
name that was used in
the early days of machine learning
and it's kinda stuck, Because
it's maybe not a great name,
for this sort of function for
mapping, from sizes of houses
to the predictions but, you know,
I think the term hypothesis
maybe isn't the best
possible in need, but this is
what, this is the
standard terminology that people using should already know.
So don't worry too, don 't
worry too much about why people call it that.
When designing a learning algorithm,
the next thing you need to decide,
is how do we
represent this hypothesis, h.
For this, and the next few
videos, I'm going to choose
our initial choice for representing
a hypothesis will be the
following we're gonna represent H,
as follows, and we're gonna write
to this h subscript theta of
x equals to
theta zero plus theta one
of x, and as a
short hand, sometimes instead
of writing, you know, h
subscript theta of x sometimes
as a shorthand I'll just write
this as h of x.
But more often I'll write it
as a subscript data, over there.
And, plotting to some pictures,
all this means is that, we
are going to, you know
predict that Y, is the
linear function of x. Right?
So, that's our data set,
and what this function is
doing, is it's predicting, that
At Y, is some straight
line function of x.  X
equals three to zero, plus
three to 1x, OK?
And, why a linear function?
Well, sometimes we'll want
to fit more complicated, perhaps non-linear functions as well.
But since this linear case
is a simple building block, we'll start
with this example first of fitting
linear functions, and we'll build
on this to eventually have
more complex models and more
complex learning algorithms,
let me also give this particular model a name.
This model is called
linear regression, or this particular
example is actually linear regression
with one variable, with the
variable being x, right?
So predicting housing prices as functions
of one variable x and, another
name for this model is univariate
linear regression, and univariate
is just a fancy way
of saying, one variable.
So that's linear regression.
In the next video we'll
start to talk about just how we go about implementing this model.