In this video we'll define something called the cost function.
This will let us figure out
how to fit the best possible straight line to our data.
In linear regression we have
a training set like that shown
here, with number of notation
"M" was the number
of training examples so maybe
M equals 47, and the
form of our hypothesis, which
we use to make predictions is this linear function.
To use a little
bit more terminology, these theta
zero and theta one, right these thetarized
are what I call the parameters of
the model, and what
we're going to do in this
video is talk about how
to go about choosing these two
parameter values, theta 0, and theta 1.
With different choices of
the parameters theta 0, and
theta 1 we get different hypothesis,
different hypothesis function.
I know some of you will
probably be already familiar with
what I'm going to do on
the slide, but just to review here are a few examples.
If theta zero is 1.5
and theta one is zero, then
the hypothesis function will look
like this because your
hypothesis function will be h
of x, equals one point
five plus, you know
zero, times x, which
is this constant value function
which is flat, at 1.5.
If theta zero equals zero,
that a one equals 0.5, then
the hypothesis will look like
this and it
should pass through this point 2,1
since you now have h
of x, really h of subscript
theta of h, but sometimes
I'll just omit theta for brevity.
So J of x would be
equal to just 0.5 times
x, which looks like that,
and finally if this equals 1,
and theta 1 equals 0.5,
then we end up with
a hypothesis that looks like this.
And it should pass through, the
2,2 point, like so,
and this is my new h
of x or my new h
subscript theta of x. All right, whatever
you remember I said
that this h subscript theta of
x, but as a short hand
sometimes I just write this
as h of x.   In
many regression, we have a
training set, like maybe the one I've plotted here.
What we want to do,
is, come up with values
for the parental state of zero, and theta one.
So for the straight line we
get all of this, corresponds to
a straight line that somehow fits the data well.
It may be that line over there.
So how do you come up
with values theta zero,
theta one, that corresponds to good fitting data?
The idea is we get
to choose our points as data zero data
one, so that h
of x, meaning the value
we predict on h of
x, that this is
at least close, to the
values y for the examples
in our training set, for our
training example so, in our
training set we're given a
number of examples where we know
x the house and we
know the actual price it will sell for.
So let's try to choose values
for the parameters so that at
least in the training set, given
the x's in the training
set we make reasonably accurate predictions
for the y values.
Let's formalize this.
So then in regression, what we're
going to do is I'm going
to want to solve
a minimization problem.
I'm going to minimize over theta zero, theta one.
And I wanted this
to be small, right?
I want the difference between h of x and y to be small.
And one thing I might do
is try to minimize the square
difference between the output
of the hypothesis and the
actual price of a horse, okay?
So, let's fill in some details.
You remember that I was using
the notation x i,
y i to represent
then the ith trainee is apple.
So I what I want really
is to sum over my
training set, sum of
i1 to m of
the squared difference between, this
is the prediction of my
hypothesis when it
is input the size of
house number i, minus the
actual prize that house number
i was sold for and
I want to minimize, some of
the training set, sum of i1
to m, up the
difference of the squared
error, squared difference to predict
the price of a house and the
price that it was actually sold for.
And just to remind you, the
notation m here was
the size of my training set, mate.
So, what will end there is
that my number of training examples.
The hash signs abbreviation.
A number of training examples.
Okay?
And to make some of
our later math a little
bit easier, I'm actually
going to look at,
you know, 1 over m, times that.
So we'll try to minimize
the average over, we're going to minimize 1 by 2m.
Putting the two, the constant, you
know, one half in front of.
It just makes some of math a little bit easier.
So minimizing one half of something
should give you the same values
for the current status of zero theta one as minimizing that function.
And just make sure that
this equation is clear, right,
this expression in here, h
subscript theta of x.
This is my, this is our usual, right?
That's equal to this, plus theta 1 xi.
And this notation, minimize
over theta zero, theta one,
just means you'll find me
the values of theta zero
and theta one that causes This expression to be minimized.
And this expression depends on theta z and theta one.
Okay?
So, just to recap, we're
posing this problem as, "Find
me the values of theta zero
and theta one so that the
average, or really 1
over 2m times the sum
of square errors between my
predictions on the training set
minus the actual values of
houses on the training set, is minimized."
So this is going to
be my overall objective function for linear regression.
And just to rewrite this out a little more cleanly.
What I am going to do is,
by convention we usually define
a cost function, which is
going to be exactly this, that
formula that I have up here.
And what I want
to do is minimize over
theta zero and theta
one my function, which
of theta zero comma theta
one, where it just merges out.
This is my cost function.
So this cost function
is also called the squared error function.
I sometimes call it
the squared error cost function.
And it turns out that. Why
do we, you know, take the squares of the errors?
It turns out that the
squared error cost function is a
reasonable choice and will work
well for most problems, for most regression problems.
There are a lot of other cost functions
that will work pretty well, but
the squared error cost function is
probably the most commonly used one for regression problems.
We can talk about alternative cost
functions as well, but this
choice that we just had should
be pretty reasonable thing to try for most linear regression problems.
Okay.
So that's the cost function.
So far we've Just seeing a
mathematical definition of, you know, this cost function.
And in case this function
j of theta zero theta one,
in case this function seems a
little bit abstract and you
still don't have a good
sense of what it's doing, in
the next video, in the
next couple videos, I'm actually
going to go a little
bit deeper into what the
cost function j is
doing and try to give
you better intuition about what
it's computing and why we want to use it.