In the previous video, we gave
a mathematical definition of the cost option.
In this video, let's look at
some examples to get that
intuition about what the
cost option is doing, and why we want to use it.
To recap, here's where we had lost time.
We want to illustrate our theater
so we had this form as a hypothesis
with these parameters, theta zero and theta one.
And, with different choices of the
parameters, we end up with
different straight lines that's in
the data, which are about
like so, and there's our
cost function and that was our optimization objective.
For this video in order
to better visualize the cost
function j, I'm going to
work with a simplified hypothesis function
like that shown on the right.
So, I'm going to use my simplify
hypothesis which is just theta
one times x.  We can,
number one, think of this as
setting the parameter theta 0 equal to 0.
So, I have only
parameter of theta 1 and
my cost function is somewhat
four accepted now h of
x. That is now
equal to just theta one times
x. And I have
only one parameter, theta one, and
so my optimization objective is
to minimize j of theta one.
In pictures, what this means
is that if theta zero
equals zero, that response
to choosing over the hypothesis
functions that pass through the
origin, that pass through the .00 over there.
Using the simplified definition of
the hypothesis in cost function,
let's try to understand the cost
function concept better.
It turn out that two key functions we want to understand.
The first is the hypothesis
function; the second is the cost function.
So notice that the hypothesis,
right, h of x, for a
fixed value of theta one, this is
a function of x.
So the hypothesis is a
function of what is the
size of the house x. In
contrast The cost function, j,
that's the function of the
parameter theta 1, which
controls the slope of the straight line.
Let's plot these functions and
try to understand them both better.
Let's start with a hypothesis.
On the left, let's say
here's my training set with three points at 11, 22 and 33.
Let's pick a
value of theta 1, and we'll say theta 1 equals 1.
And if that's my choice for
theta 1, then my hypothesis
is going to look like this straight line over here.
OK?
And I'll point out, when
I'm plotting my hypothesis function, my
x-axis, my horizontal axis,
is labeled x, is labeled the
size of the holes over here.
Now, I have temporarily
set theta 1 equals 1.
What I want to do
is figure out is, what
is j of theta
1 when theta 1 equals 1.
So, let's go ahead
and compute the cost function
is for the value one.
Well as usual my cost function
is defined as follows right,
some from, someone with
my training sense of this
usual squared error term
and this is therefore
equal to this of
theta one xi minus
yi and if
you simplify, this turns out
to be that 0
square to 0 square to 0
square, which is of
course just equals to 0.
Now, inside the cost function,
it turns out each of this
terms here is equals to
0 because for the specific
training sets I have where my three
training examples are at one
one two two three three, if
theta one is equal to
one then h of
x, my h of xi
is equal yi exactly.
Let's put this together.
Right?
And so, h of
x minus y; each of
these terms is equal to zero
which is why I find that
j of one is equal
to zero, so we
now know that j of
one is equal
to zero, that's all that.
What I am going to do on
the right is plot my
cost function J, and notice
because my cost function is
a function of my parameter theta one.
When I plot my cost function,
the horizontal axis is now
labeled with theta one.
So I have j of one 00.
So, let's go ahead and
plot that to
hand off your and x over there.
Now, let's look at some other examples.
If theta 1 can take on arrange of different values, right?
So, if theta 1 can take
on the negative value, zero, positive values.
So, what if theta one is
equal to o point five?
What happens then?
Let's go ahead and plot that.
I'm now going to set
eight theta one equals zero point
five and in that case my hypothesis
now looks like this as the
line was sloped equals to
o point five and let's
compute j of 0.5.
So that is going
to be one over two
m of my usual cross function.
It turns out that the cross
function is going to be
the sum of square
values of the height
of this line, plus
the sum of square of the
height of that line, plus the
sum of square of the height of that line.
Right.
Because this virtual difference, that's
the difference between, you know,
y, i and the
predicted value h of the xi, right?
So the first example is going
to be 0.5 minus 1 squared,
because my hypothesis predicted
0.5, whereas the actual
value was 1.
So, my second example
I get 1 minus 2
squared because my hypothesis
predicted 1 where the actual housing price
was 2 and then finally,
plus 1.5 minus 3 there
and so that's equal to
one over two times three
because m, my
training set size have three
training examples, and then
that's times, simplifying the thing
in parenthesis is 3.5, so
that's 3.5 over 6 which is
about 0.68.
So now we
know about j of 0.5 is about 0.68.
Let's go and
plot that, oh excuse me math error.
It is actually 0.58.
So I'm going to plot that
which is maybe about over there, okay.
Now, let's do one
more, how about if
theta 1 is equal to zero.
What is j of zero
equal to?
It turns out if that if
theta 1 is equal to 0
then h of x
is just equal to, you
know, this flat line.
Right, if this goes horizontally like this.
And so measuring the errors,
we have that j of 0
is equal to 1/2m times
1 squared + 2 squared
+ 3 squared, which
is 1/6 times
14, which is about 2.3.
So let's go ahead and plot that as well.
You end up with a value around 2.3.
And, of course, we can keep
on doing this for other values of theta one.
It turns out that you can
have negative values of theta one as well.
So if theta one
is negative, then h
of x would be equal to,
say, -0.5 times x, right,
if negative theta 1 is -0.5.
And so that corresponds to
a hypothesis, you know, with
a slope of negative -0.5.
And you can actually keep on computing these errors.
This turns out to be,
you know, for 0.5, it
turns out to really high
however, it works out
to be something like 5.25
and so on, and
the different values of
theta 1 you can
compute these things, right and
it turns out the computer link
of values, you get something
like that and by computing
range of values you can actually,
slowly you trace out what
this function j of theta
will say and that's what
j of theta is.
To recap, for each value
of theta one, right, each
value of theta one corresponds
to a different hypothesis or
to a different straight line
fit on the left
and for each value if theta
1, we could then derive
a different value of j
of theta 1 and
for example, you know,
if theta 1 equals 1
corresponded to this straight
line to the data, whereas
theta 1 equals 0.5,
this point, shown in magenta,
corresponded to maybe that line.
And theta 1 equals zero,
which we'll show in
blue, that corresponds to this horizontal line.
Right?
So for each value of theta 1, we
wound up with a different value
of j of theta 1 and
we could then
use this to trace out this plot on the right.
Now, you remember, the optimization
objective for our learning algorithm
is we want to
choose the value of theta
one that minimizes
j of theta 1.
Right?
This was our objective function for linear regression.
Well, looking at this curve,
the value that minimizes theta 1
is, you know, theta 1 equals to 1.
And lo and behold, that
is indeed the best
possible straight line that
fits our data by setting theta
1 equals 1, for this
particular train set, we actually end up fitting it perfectly.
And that's why minimizing j if
theta 1 corresponds to finding
any straight line that fits the data well.
So, to wrap up,
in this video we looked at
some plus to understand the cost function.
To do so, we simplify the algorithms
so that it can only have
1 to theta 1 and we set
the parameters theta 0 to a 0.
In the next video,
we'll go back to the original
problem formulation and look
at some visualizations involving both
theta 0 and theta 1.
That is without setting theta 0
to 0 and hopefully that would
give you an even better sense
of what the cost function j is
doing in the original linear regression relation.