In this video, this dug deeper
and get even better intuition about what the cost function is doing.
This video is to use that you're familiar with conswell plots.
If you're not familiar with contour
plots or contour figures, some
of the illustrations in this
video may or may not make sense to you.
But it's okay, and if
you end up skipping this video, or
if some of it doesn't quite make
sense because you haven't seen contour
before, that's okay and
you still understand the rest
of this clause without those parts of it.
Here's our problem formulation as
usual with the hypothesis, parameters,
cost function and our optimization objective.
I like a four and like
the last video, I'm going to
keep both of my parent's
theta 0 and theta
1 as we generate our visualizations for the cost function.
So, same as last time,
we went on the stand, the
hypothesis h and the
cost function j. So, here's
my training set of Housing prices
and let's pick some hypothesis,
you know, like that one.
This is not a particularly good
hypothesis, but if I
set theta 0 equals 50
and theta 1 equals 0.06,
then I end up
with this hypothesis down here,
and that corresponds to that straight line.
Now, given these values of
theta 0 and theta 1, we
want to plot the corresponding,
you know, cost function on the right.
What we did last time was,
when we only have theta
1, you know, we were drawing
plots that look like this as a function of theta 1.
But now we have two
parameters, theta 0 and
theta 1 and so the
plot gets a little more complicated.
It turns out that when we
had only one parameter that the
plots we drew had this sort of bow-shaped function.
Now when we have two
parameters, it turns out the
cost function also has a
similar sort of bow shape and
in fact, depending on your
training set, you might get a
cost function that maybe looks
something like this so this
is a 3D surface plot
where the axes are labeled
theta zero and theta one.
So, as you vary theta
0 and theta 1, the 2
parameters, you get different
values of the cost function,
j of theta 0, of theta 1.
And the height of
this surface of both the
particular point theta z or
theta 1, right that's the
vertical axis, the height of
the surface of the points indicates
the value of j of theta 0, j of theta 1.
And you can see
it sort of has this bow-like shape.
Let me show you the same positive 3D.
So, here's the same
figure in 3D, we're back to
theta 0, theta 1 and
vertical access j of theta 0, theta 1.
And if I rotate this, you
know, plot around, you kind
of get a sense, I hope, of this dull shape surface.
That's what the cost function j looks like.
Now for the purpose of
illustration in the rest of
this video, I'm not actually going
to use to these sorts of 3D
surfaces to show you
the as function J. Instead,
I'm going to use contour plots,
or what I also
call contour figures-- I guess
they mean the same thing--to show
you these surfaces So, here's
an example of a contour
figure shown on the right,
where the axes are
theta 0 and theta 1.
And what each of
these ovals, each of
these ellipses, shows is a
set of points that takes
on the same value for
J of theta 0, theta 1.
So, car 3T, for
example, this you take
that point and that point and that point.
All three of these points, that
I just drew in magenta, they
have the same value for J of theta 0, theta 1.
OK?
Where these are theta 0,
theta 1 axes, but those three
have the same value for
J of theta 0, theta 1.
And if you haven't seen
contour plots much before, think
of, imagine if you will
a bow-shaped function that's coming
out of my screen so that
the minimum, so the bottom
of the boat is this point
right there, this middle of
these concentric ellipsis, and imagine
a bow shape that grows out
of my screen like this, so
that each of these ellipses has
the same height above my screen
and minimum of the bow is right down there.
And so the quantal figure is
a way to, is maybe a
more convenient way, to visualize
my function j.
So,
let's look at some examples.
Over here I have
a particular point, this is
with theta 0 equals
about 800, and theta
1 equals a
minus 115, and so this
point in red
corresponds to one particular
pair of values of theta zero, comma theta zero 1.
And they correspond in fact,
to that hypothesis, theta zero
is about 800, it intersects the vertical
axis at around 800 and this
is the slope of about -.15.
Now this line is
really not such a good fit to the data, right?
This hypothesis, H(x), with these
values of theta 0, theta
1, is really not such a
good fit to the data and
so, you find that its cost
is a value that's out here.
It's, you know, pretty far from the minimum.
Right?
It's pretty far, this is
a pretty high cost because this
is just not that good of a fit to the data.
Let's look at some more examples.
Now here's a different hypothesis
that's, you know, still not
a fit for the data, but maybe slightly better.
So here, right, that's
my point that those
are my parameters, theta 0, theta
1, and so, my
theta 0 value, that's
about 360, and my value
for theta 1 is equal to
zero, so, you know, let's break that out.
Theta 0 equals 360.
Theta 1 equals 0.
And this pair of
parameters corresponds to that
hypothesis corresponds to a flat line, right?
This is h of x equals
360 plus 0 times x.
So, that's my hypothesis and
this hypotheses again have some
cost and that cost
is, you know, plotted as
the height of the j
function at that point.
Let's look at just this a couple of examples.
Here's one more.
You know, at this value
of theta 0 and
at that value of theta
1, we end up with
this hypothesis, h of
x, and again not the
great input to the data and just
actually, you can even further fit in well.
Last example.
Well, this is actually
not quite at the minimum, but it's pretty close to the minimum.
So, this is not such a
bad fit to the data
where for a particular value of
theta 0 whatever this
value is and for physical
value of theta 1, we
get a physical of h of
x and this is not quite the minimum.
This is pretty close and so,
the sum of square the errors
that some square distances between my
training examples and my hypothesis.
That's the sum of squared
distances of all of these errors.
This is pretty close to the minimum, even though it's not quite the minimum.
So, with these figures, I hope
that gives you a better understanding
of what values of
the cost function j, how
the r and how that corresponds
to different hypotheses as well as
how better hypotheses may
correspond to points that closer
to the minimum of this cost
function j.
Now, of
course, what we really what
is an efficient algorithm like
the efficient piece of software
for automatically finding the
value of theta 0 theta
1 that minimizes the cost function j.
What we don't want to
do is have to write
software to plot out this
point and then try to manually
read off the numbers.
That this is not a good
way to do it, and in fact, we'll see it
later that when we
look at more complicated examples, we
will have high dimensional figures with
more parameters, that it turns
out we'll see and
later in the scores' examples where
This figure here, cannot really
be plotted, has become much
harder to visualise, and so
what we want is to have
software to find the value
of theta 0, theta 1 that
minimizes this function and in
the next video, we'll start
to talk about an algorithm
for automatically finding that
value of theta 0 and
theta 1 that minimizes the cost function j.