We've previously defined the cost
function J.  In this video,
I want to tell you about
an algorithm, called gradient descent,
for minimizing the cost
function J.  It turns
out a gradient descent is a
more general algorithm and is
used not only in linear regression.
It's actually used all over the
place in machines or anything and
later in the class we'll use gradient descent
to minimize other functions as
well not just the cost
function j for linear regression.
So, in this video, we'll just
hop on gradient descent for
minimizing some arbitrary function
J and then in
later videos we'll take those
algorithms and apply specifically to
the cost function J that
we had to find for the linear regression.
So, here's the problem set up.
Going to see that we have
some function j of theta(
0), theta(1), maybe it's
a cost function from linear regression,
maybe it's some other function we
want to minimize and
we want to come up with
an algorithm for minimizing
that as a function of j
of theta 0 of theta 1.
So, just as a sign,
it turns out that gradient
descent actually Applies to more general functions.
So imagine if you have
a function that's a function
of J as theta 0, theta
1, theta 2, up
to say, sub theta n,
and you want to minimize
theta zero, minimise over theta
zero up to theta
n of this j
of theta zero up to
theta n.
It turns out
gradient descent is an algorithm
for solving this general problem,
but for the sake of brevity,
for the sake of succinctness
of notation, I'm just going
to pretend I have only two
parameters throughout the rest of this video.
Here's the idea for gradient descent.
What we're going to do is
we 're going to start off
with some initial guesses for theta 0 and theta 1.
Doesn't really matter what they
are, but a common choice would
be a reset theta 0
to state zero and set theta 1 to zero.
Just initialize them to zero.
What we're going to do
in gradient descent is we'll keep
changing theta zero and
zeta one a little bit, to
try to reduce j or
theta zero and theta one, so
hopefully we wind up at
a minimum or a local minimum
So, let's see what,
lets see pictures of what gradient descent does.
Let's say you tried to minimize these functions.
Notice the axes.
This is theta 0, theta
1 on the horizontal axes and J is the vertical axis.
And so the height of the
surface shows J. And we want to minimize this function.
So we're going to start off
at with theta 0, theta 1 at some point.
So imagine, picking some value
for theta 0, theta 1, and
that corresponds to starting at
some point on the surface
of this function.
So whatever value of theta 0, theta 1, gives you some point here.
I didn't initialize them to
0 - 0, but sometimes you can
initialize to other values as well.
Now, I want you to imagine
that this figure shows a hole.
Imagine this is the landscape
of some grassy park, with
two hills like so, and
I want you to imagine
that you are physically standing at
that point on this little red hill in your park.
In grading descent what we're going
to do is spin 360
degrees around, just look
all around us and ask
If I were to take a
little baby step in some
direction and I want
to go down hill as quickly
as possible, what direction do
I take that little baby step
in if I want to go
down, if I want to
physically walk down this hill as rapidly as possible?
It turns out that if
you are standing at that point on
a hill and you look all
around, you find that the
best direction to take a
little step downhill is roughly that direction.
OK?
And now you're at this new
point on your hill,
and you're going to again look all
around and then say, "What
direction should I step in
order to take a little baby step downhill?"
And if you do that and take
another step, you take a step in that direction.
And then you keep going.
You know, from this new point you
look around and decide what
direction will take you downhill most quickly.
Take another step, another step
and so on, until you converge
to this local minimum down here.
Gradient descent is an interesting property.
This first time we ran
gradient descent, we were starting
at this point over here Starting at that point over here.
Now imagine, we initialize gradient
descent just a couple of steps to the right.
Imagine we initialize gradient
descent with that point on the upper right.
If you were to repeat this process
and stop at that point, look
all around, take a little
step in the direction of steepest
descent, you would do
that, then look around and
take another step and so on.
And if you started just a
couple steps to the right,
gradient descent would have taken
you to this second
local optimum over on the right.
So, if you had started
at this first point, you would have wound up at this local optimum.
But if you started just a little
bit, slightly different location, you
would have wound up at a very different local optimum.
And, this is a property of
gradient descent that we'll say a little more about later.
So, that's the intuition in pictures.
Let's look at the map.
This is the defintion of the gradient descent algorithm.
We are going to just repeatedly do
this until convergence.
We are going to update my parameter,
theta j, by taking
theta j and subtracting from
it alpha times this term over here.
Okay?
So let's see.
The law of details in this equations so let me unpack some of it.
First this notation here,
colon equals, we're going
to use colon equals to denote
assignment, the assignment operator,
so concretely if I write
A:B, what this means
take the value in B
and use it to overwrite whether
the value is A.
So, this
means you'll set A to be
equal to the value of B.
It's assignment, and I can
also do a colon equals A + 1.
This means take A and increase its value by 1.
Whereas in contrast, if
I use the equals sign,
if we write AB, then this
is a truth assertion.
So if I write AB, then
I'm asserting that the value
of A equals to the
value of B. So
the left hand side, that's a computer operation.
We've set the value of A to B value.
The right hand side, this is asserting.
I'm just making a claim that the values of A and B are the same.
And so, whereas if we
write A:A+1, that increment A by 1.
Hopefully, I won't ever write
AA+1, because that's just wrong, right?
A and A+1 can never
be equal to the same values, okay?
So that's the first part of the definition.
This alpha here
is a number that
is called the learning rate, and
what alpha does, is it
basically controls how big
a step we take downhill with gradient descent.
So if alpha is very large,
then that corresponds to a very
aggressive gradient descent procedure
where we are trying to take huge
steps downhill, and if
alpha is very small then we're
taking little, little baby steps downhill.
And I'll come back and say
more about this later, about how
to set alpha and so on.
And finally, this term here.
That's a derivative term.
I don't want to talk about
it right now, but I will
derive this derivative term and
tell you exactly what this is later.
Some of you will
be more familiar with calculus than
others, but even if you
aren't familar with calculus, don't worry about it.
I'll tell you what you need to know about this term here.
Now, there's one more
subtlety about gradient descents, which
is in gradient descent
we are going to update theta(0) and theta(1).
So, this update takes place where J0 and J1.
So, update theta(0) and update theta(1).
And the subtlety of how
you create gradient descentfor this expression,
for this update equation, you
want to simultaneously update theta
zero and theta one.
What I mean by that,
is that in this equation we're
going to update theta zero :
theta zero minus something and update
theta one : theta one minus
something and the way
to implement this is you
should compute the right
hand side, compute that
thing for theta zero
and theta one, and then
simultaneously, at the same
time, update theta zero and theta one.
And so let me say
what I mean by that, this
is a correct implantion of create
a descend meaning simultaneous updates.
I'm going to set ten zero equals
that, set ten one equals that
so basic compute the right hand
sides and then having
computed the right hand side
and store them in two variables
ten zero and ten one and
you're going to update theta zero
and theta one simultaneously, that's
a correct implantation.
In contrast, here's an incorrect
implantion that does not do
a simultaneous update.
So in this incorrect implantation
we compute Ten zero and
then we update theta zero, then
we compute ten one and we update ten one.
And the difference between the right
hand side and left hand side
computations is that if
you look down here, you look
at this step, if by
this time you have already updated
theta zero, then you
would be using the new value
of theta zero to compute
this derivative term and so
this gives you a different
value of ten one than
the left hand side because you've
now plugged in the new
value of theta zero into
this equation, and so this
on the right hand side is not a correct implementation.
So I don't
want to say why you need to do the simultaneous updates.
It turns out that the way
gradient descent is usually implemented,
it actually turns out
to be more natural to implement
the simultaneous updates, and when
people talk about gradient
descent, they always mean simultaneous updates.
implement the non-simultaneous update,
it turns out it will probably
work anyway, but this algorithm
on the right is not what
people refer to as gradient
descend and this is some other algorithm with different properties.
For various reasons this
can behave in slightly stranger ways
and what you should do
is really update the simultaneous updates of gradient descent.
So that's the outline of the gradient descent algorithim.
In the next video we're going
to go into the details
of the derivative term, which I wrote out but didn't really define.
If you have taken a calculus
class before and if you
are familiar with partial derivatives
and derivatives it turns out
that's exactly what that derivative
is, but in case you
aren't familiar with calculus, don't worry about it.
The next book here will give you
all the intutions and tell you
everything you need to know
to compute that derivative term,
even if you haven't seen calculus
or even if you haven't seen partial
derivatives before and
with that with the next
video hopefully you will be
able to give you all the
intuition you need to apply gradient descent