In the previous video, we gave
a mathematical definition of gradient descent.
Let's go deeper, and in this
video get better intuition about
what the algorithm is doing,
and why the steps of the
gradient descent algorithm might make sense.
Here's the gradient descent algorithm that
we saw last time and
I just remind you, this
parameter, or this term
alpha, is called the learning
rate, and it controls
how big a step we
take when updating my parameter
theta j and this
second term here is the derivative term.
And what I want to do, in
this video, is give you
about what each of
these two terms is doing, and
why, when put together, this entire update makes sense.
In order to convey these
intuitions, what I want
to do is use a slightly
simple example where we
want to minimize a function
of just one parameter, so we
have a cost function
j of just one parameter theta
one, like we did a few
videos back, where theta
one is a real number ok.
So, we can have 1d plots which are rather simple to look at.
Let's try to understand what gradient descent will do on this function.
So, let's say here's
my function j of
theta one, and so that's
my and where theta
one is a real number.
Right?
Now, let's have initialized gradient
descent with theta one
at this location, so imagine
that we start off at that point of my function.
What gradient descent will do
is it will update theta one.
Let's update to this, theta
one minus alpha times dd
theta one j of theta one.
Right?And
as in the side, this derivative term, right?
And if you're wondering
why I changed the notation from these partial derivative symbols.
If you don't know what the difference
is between these partial derivative symbols
and the DD theta, don't worry about it.
Technically, in mathematics, we call
this a partial derivative, we call
this a derivative, depending on
the number of parameters in
the function 'J', but that's
mathematical technicality, so for
the purpose of this lecture think
of these partial symbols and
gd theta one as exactly
the same thing and don't worry about whether there is differences.
I' m going to try to use the mathematically-precise notation.
But for our purposes, DC notations are really the same thing.
So let's see what this equation will do.
So, we're going to compute this derivative.
I'm not sure if
you've seen derivatives in calculus before,
but what a derivative
at this point does, is basically
say, let's take the
tangent to that point, that
straight line, that red line is just touching this function.
Let's look at the slope of this red line.
That's what the derivative is.
It says, what's the slope
Of the line that is just tangent to the function.
OK, and the slope of
the line, of course, is just,
this height divided by this horizontal thing.
Now This line has a positive slope.
So it has a positive
derivative, and so
my update to theta is
going to be theta 1
gets updated as theta 1
minus alpha times some positive number.
Alpha, the learning rate, is
always a positive number, and
so I'm going to take theta
one gives update as theta
one minus something, so I'm
going to end up moving theta 1 to the left.
We're going to decrease theta 1,
and we can see this
is the right thing to do, because
as you want to head in this direction
to get me closer to the minimum over there.
So gradient descent, so far, seems to be doing the right thing.
Let's look at another example.
So let's take my same function
J of theta
one and now let's say
I had instead initialized my parameter over there on the left.
So theta one is here, I'm going to adapt point on the surface.
Now, my derivative term, DD
Theta 1, J of Theta
1, when you evaluate to that
this point, going to look
at the slope
of that line, so this
derivative term is a slope of this line.
But this line is slanting down.
So this line has negative slope.
Right.
Or alternatively, I could
say that this function has a
negative derivative (which just means negative slope) at that point.
So this is less than or equal to zero.
So when I update Theta,
Theta is updated as
Theta minus Alpha times a
negative number.
So I have theta one
minus a negative number, which
means I'm actually going to
increase data, right because
this is minus, of a negative
number, that means I'm adding
something with data, and what
that means is that I'm going
to end up increasing data, and
so we'll start here and increase
theta, which again seems
like the thing I wanted to
do, to try to get
me closer to the minimum.
So this hopefully explains the
intuition behind what the
derivative term is doing,
let's next take a look
at the learning rates from alpha,
and try to figure out what that's doing.
So, here's my theta
descent update rule, right, it's
this equation, so let's
look at what can
happen if alpha is either
too small, or alpha is too large.
So this first example, what happens if alpha is too.
So here's my function J
- J of theta.
Let's say I start here.
If alpha's too small, then
what I'm going to do is multiply
my update by some small number,
so I end up taking a baby step like that.
Ok?
So that's one step we've already said.
Then from this new point I'm
going to take another step -but if
alpha's too small I'll
take another little baby
step and so
if my loaning rate is too
small, I'm going to
end up taking these tiny,
tiny baby steps, to try
to get to the minimum, and I'm
going to need a lot of steps
to get to the minimum, and so
if alpha's too small, gradient
descent can be slow because I'm
just going to take these tiny, tiny
baby steps, so it's going
to need a lot of steps
before it gets anywhere close to the local minimum.
Now, how about if alpha's too large?
So here's my function J of theta.
Turns out, if alpha's too
large then gradient descent
can overshoot the minimum and
even fail to converge,
or even diverge, so here's what I mean.
Let's say I start off theta there that's pretty close the minimum.
So the derivative points to the
right, but if alpha's
too big, I'm going to
take a huge step - a huge step like that.
So I'm going to end up taking a huge step.
And now my cost function's actually gotten
worse cause I start with
this value, but now, my value's actually got worse.
Now my derivative, you know,
points to the left and says I should decrease data.
But if my loaning rate is
too big, I may take a
huge step going from here all the way out there.
So I end up going out
there, right, and if
my loaning rate is too big
I can take another huge step on
the next acceleration, I kind of
overshoot, and overshoot, and
so on, until you'll notice
I'm getting further and further
away from the minimum.
And so if alpha's too large
it can fail to converge or even diverge.
Now, I have another question for you.
So this is a tricky
one, and when I was
first learning this stuff, it actually took me a long time to figure this out.
But what if your parameter alpha
one is already at the local minimum?
What do you think one step of gradient descent will do?
So, let's suppose to you
initialize theta one at a local minimum.
So suppose this is
your initial value of theta one
over here, and it's
already at a local optimum, the local minimum.
It depends on the local optimum, your
derivative will be equal
zero so that slope that
tangent point so the
slope of this line
will be equal to
zero and, thus, this
derivative term is equal to zero.
And so, in your gradient
descent update, you have theta(1)
gets updated as theta(1) minus
alpha times 0.
And so, what this means
is that, if you're already
at a local optimum, it leaves
theta(1) unchanged, because you
see it updates as theta(1)  equals theta(1).
So, if your parameters
are already at a local minimum,
one step of gradient descent does absolutely nothing.
It doesn't change the parameter,
which is what you want because
it keeps your solution at
the local optimum.
This also explains why gradient descent
can converge to local minimum
even with the learning rate alpha fixed.
Here's what I mean by that.
Let's look at an example.
So, here's a cost function
J, or theta, that maybe I wanna minimize.
And let's say I initialize
my algorithm, my gradient
descent algorithm up there, at that magenta point.
if I take one step of gradient
descent, maybe it'll take me
to that point, because my derivative's pretty steep out there, right?
Now, I'm at this
green point, and if
I take another step on green
descent you'll notice my
derivative, meaning the slope
is less steep at the
green point compared to
at the magenta point out there.
Because as I approach the
minimum, my derivative get closer
and closer to zero as
I approach the minimum.
So, after one step of
gradient descent, my new derivative
is a little bit smaller, so when
I take another step of gradient
descent, I will naturally,
take a small step from
this green point to the magenta point.
Now from the new point to the red point.
Now I'm even closer to the
minimum, so the derivative here
will be even smaller than it was at the green point.
So I want to take another step of gradient descent.
Now, my derivative term is even smaller.
And so the magnitude of the
update to theta 1
is even smaller so take a
smaller step like so, and as
gradient descent runs you will
automatically take smaller and
smaller steps until eventually
you are taking very small steps,
you know, and you find the
conversion to the, to the local minimum.
So, just to recap, in
gradient descent, as we approach
a local minimum, gradient descent
will automatically take smaller steps,
and that's because as we approach
the local minimum, by definition
the local minimum is when you
know there is derivative equal to zero.
So as we approach the local minimum
this derivative term will automatically
get smaller and so
gradient descent will automatically take
smaller steps, so this
is what gradient descent looks like,
and so actually no need
to decrease alpha over time.
So that's the gradient
descent algorithm, and you can
use it to minimise, to try
to minimise any cost function J,
not the cost function J we defined from linear regression.
In the next video, we're going
to take the function J and
set that back to be
exactly linear regression's cost function,
the square cost function that we
came up with earlier, and taking
gradient descent and square cost
function and putting them together,
that will give us our first learning algorithm.
That will give us our linear regression algorithm.