You now know about linear regression and gradient descent.
The plan from here on out
is to tell you about a
couple important extensions of these ideas.
Concretely here they are.
First, it turns out that in
order to solve this minimization
problem, turns out there's
an algorithm for solving for
theta 0 and theta 1
exactly without needing an
iterative algorithm without needing
this algorithm like gradient descent that
we had to innovate you know, multiple times over.
So, it turns out there are
advantages and disadvantages of this
algorithm that you just saw
for theta 0 and theta
1 so basically just in one shot.
One advantage is that there
is no longer a learning rate
alpha that you need to
worry about, and set, and
so it can be much faster for some problems.
We'll see about advantages and disadvantages later.
Second we are going to talk
about algorithms for learning
with a larger number of features.
So, so far we've been
learning with just one feature,
the size of the house and using that to predict the price.
So we are trying to take x
and using that to predict y.
Before other learning problems,
we may have a larger number of features.
So for example let's say that
you know not only the size,
but also the number of bedrooms,
the number of floors and the
age of home of these
houses and when you want
to use that to predict the price of the houses.
In that case, maybe we'll
call these features x1, x2, x3, and x4.
So now we have
four features, want to
use these four features to predict
why the price of the house.
It turns out with all of
these features, and four of
them in this case, it turns out
that with multiple features, it
becomes harder to plot or to visualize the data.
So for example, you know,
we try to plot to this type of data set.
Maybe we'll have the vertical
axis be the price, and
maybe we can have one
axis here and another
one here with this axis
is the size of the house
and that axis is the number of bedrooms.
Yeah.
But this is just plotting my
first two features, size and
number of bedrooms and when we
have these additional features, I
just don't know how the plot
all of these data right, because
I need a quarter inch figure.
I don't really know how to plot.
You know, something more than like
a three dimensional figure over here.
Also, as you can tell, the
notation starts to get a little more complicated, right?
So, rather than just having X
our features, we now have
X1 through X4,
and we're using these
subscripts to denote my four different features.
It turns out the best notation
to keep all of this straight
and to understand what's going on
with the data even when we
don't quite know how to plot
it, it turns out that the
best notation is the notation of linear algebra.
Linear algebra gives a notation
and a set of things, or a
set of operations, that we can
do with matrices and vectors.
For example, here's a matrix
where the columns of
this matrix are, the
first column is the size
of the 4 houses, the second
column is the number of bedrooms,
that's the number of floors and that's the age of the home.
And so the matrix is this
block of numbers that lets
me take all of my data,
all of my axis and all
of my features and organize them into.
Instead of one big block of numbers like that.
And here is what
we call a vector in linear
algebra, where the four
numbers here are the
prices of the four
houses that we saw on the previous slide.
So, in the next
set of videos, what I'm
going to do is do a quick review of linear algebra.
If you haven't seen matrices and
vectors before, so if all
of this, everything on this slide is brand new to you.
Or if you see
linear algebra before but it's
been a while so you aren't
completely familiar with it anymore,
then please watch the next set
of videos and I'll quickly
review the linear algebra you
need in order to implement
and use the more powerful versions of linear regression.
It turns out linear algebra isn't
just useful for linear regression
models, but these ideas
of matrices and vectors will
be useful for helping us
to implement and actually get
computationally efficient implementations for
many later Mission Learning models as well.
And as you can tell,
these sorts of matrices and vectors
will give us an efficient way to
start to organize a light
amounts of data when working with larger training sets.
So, in case you're
not familiar with linear
algebra, or in case linear algebra seems
like a complicated little scary
concept, if you've never seen it before.
Don't worry about it.
It turns out in order to
implement machinery algorithms, we need
only the very, very basics of
linear algebra and you'll be
able to very quickly pick
up everything you need to know in the next few videos.
Concretely, to decide
if you should watch the
next set of videos, here are the topics I'm am going to cover.
Talk about what are matrices and vectors
and talk about how to add,
subtract, multiply matrices and vectors
and talk about the ideas of matrix inverses and transposes.
And so if you sure
if you should watch the next set
of videos, take a look at these two things.
So, if you think you know
how to compute this quantity, that's
is a matrix transfer times another matrix.
You think you know, if you've seen this stuff before.
If you know how to compute the
inverse of a matrix, times a
vector, minus a number times in the vector.
If these two things look completely
familiar to you, then you
can safely skip the optional
set of videos on linear algebra,
but these concepts, if you
are slightly uncertain what these
blocks of numbers, what these matrices
and numbers mean, then please
take a look at the next
set of videos, and it will
very quickly teach you what you
need to know about linear algebra
in order to program mission learning
algorithms, and deal with large amounts of data.