In this video, I'd like
to start talking about how to
multiply together two matrices.
We'll start with a special case
of that, of matrix vector
multiplication -  multiplying a matrix together with a vector.
Let's start with an example.
Here is a matrix,
and here is a vector, and
let's say we want to
multiply together this matrix
with this vector, what's the result?
Let me just work through this
example and then we
can step back and look at just what the steps were.
It turns out the result of
this multiplication process is going
to be, itself, a vector.
And I'm just going work
with this first and later we'll
come back and see just what I did here.
To get the first element of
this vector I am going
to take these two numbers
and multiply them with
the first row of the
matrix and add up the corresponding numbers.
Take one multiplied by
one, and take
three and multiply it by
five, and that's
what, that's one plus fifteen so that gives me sixteen.
I'm going to write sixteen here.
then for the second row,
second element, I am
going to take the second row
and multiply it by this vector,
so I have four
times one, plus zero
times five, which is
equal to four, so you'll have four there.
And finally for the last
one I have two one times
one five, so two
by one, plus one
by 5, which is equal
to a 7, and
so I get a 7 over there.
It turns out that the
results of multiplying that's
a 3x2 matrix by a
2x1 matrix is also
just a two-dimensional vector.
The result of this is
going to be a 3x1
matrix, so that's why
three by one 3x1
matrix, in other words
a 3x1 matrix is just a three dimensional vector.
So I realize that I
did that pretty quickly, and you're
probably not sure that you can
repeat this process yourself, but
let's look in more detail
at what just happened and what
this process of multiplying a matrix by a vector looks like.
Here's the details of how to
multiply a matrix by a vector.
Let's say I have a matrix A
and want to multiply it by
a vector x. The
result is going to be some
vector y. So the
matrix A is a m
by n dimensional matrix, so
m rows and n columns and
we are going to multiply that by a
n by 1 matrix, in other words an n dimensional vector.
It turns out this
"n" here has to match this "n" here.
In other words, the number of
columns in this matrix, so
it's the number of n columns.
The number of columns here has
to match the number of rows here.
It has to match the dimension of this vector.
And the result of this product
is going to be an n-dimensional
vector y.  Rows here.
"M" is going
to be equal to the number
of rows in this matrix "A".
So how do you actually compute this vector "Y"?
Well it turns out to compute
this vector "Y", the process
is to get "Y""I", multiply "A's"
"I'th" row with the
elements of the vector "X"
and add them up.
So here's what I mean.
In order to get the
first element of "Y",
that first number--whatever that turns
out to be--we're gonna take
the first row of the
matrix "A" and multiply
them one at a time
with the elements of this vector "X".
So I take this first number
multiply it by this first number.
Then take the second number multiply it by this second number.
Take this third number whatever
that is, multiply it the third number
and so on until you get to the end.
And I'm gonna add up the
results of these products and the
result of paying that out is going to give us this first element of "Y".
Then when we want to get
the second element of "Y", let's say this element.
The way we do that is we
take the second row of
A and we repeat the whole thing.
So we take the second row
of A, and multiply it
elements-wise, so the elements
of X and add
up the results of the products
and that would give me the
second element of Y. And
you keep going to get and we
going to take the third row
of A, multiply element Ys
with the vector x,
sum up the results and then
I get the third element and so
on, until I get down
to the last row like so, okay?
So that's the procedure.
Let's do one more example.
Here's the example:  So let's look at the dimensions.
Here, this is a three
by four dimensional matrix.
This is a four-dimensional vector,
or a 4 x 1 matrix, and
so the result of this, the
result of this product is going
to be a three-dimensional vector.
Write, you know, the vector,
with room for three elements.
Let's do the, let's carry out the products.
So for the first element, I'm
going to take these four numbers
and multiply them with the
vector X. So I have
1x1, plus 2x3,
plus 1x2, plus 5x1, which
is equal to - that's
1+6, plus 2+6, which gives me 14.
And then for the
second element, I'm going
to take this row now and
multiply it with this vector  (0x1)+3.
All right, so
0x1+  3x3 plus
0x2 plus 4x1,
which is equal to, let's
see that's 9+4, which is 13.
And finally, for the last
element, I'm going to take
this last row, so I
have minus one times one.
You have minus two, or really there's a plus next to a two I guess.
Times three plus zero
times two plus zero times
one, and so that's
going to be minus one minus
six, which is going to make
this seven, and so that's vector seven.
Okay?
So my final answer is this
vector fourteen, just to
write to that without the colors, fourteen,
thirteen, negative seven.
And as promised, the
result here is a three by one matrix.
So that's how you multiply a matrix and a vector.
I know that a lot just
happened on this slide, so
if you're not quite sure where all
these numbers went, you know,
feel free to pause the video
you know, and so take a
slow careful look at this
big calculation that we just
did and try to make
sure that you understand the steps
of what just happened to get
us these numbers,fourteen, thirteen and eleven.
Finally, let me show you a neat trick.
Let's say we have
a set of four houses so 4
houses with 4 sizes like these.
And let's say I have a
hypotheses for predicting what is
the price of a house, and
let's say I want to compute,
you know, H of X for each of my 4 houses here.
It turns out there's neat way
of posing this, applying this
hypothesis to all of my houses at the same time.
It turns out there's a neat
way to pose this as a
Matrix Vector multiplication.
So, here's how I'm going to do it.
I am going to construct a matrix as follows.
My matrix is going to be
1111 times, and I'm
going to write down the sizes
of my four houses here and
I'm going to construct a vector
as well, And my
vector is going to this
vector of two elements, that's
minus 40 and 0.25.
That's these two co-efficients;
data 0 and data 1.
And what I am going
to do is to take matrix
and that vector and multiply them
together, that times is that multiplication symbol.
So what do I get?
Well this is a
four by two matrix.
This is a two by one matrix.
So the outcome is going
to be a four by one
vector, all right.
So, let me,
so this is
going to be a 4 by
1 matrix is the outcome or
really a four diminsonal vector,
so let me write it as
one of my four elements in my four real numbers here.
Now it turns out and so
this first element of this
result, the way I
am going to get that is, I
am going to take this and multiply it by the vector.
And so this is going to
be -40 x
1 + 4.25 x 2104.
By the way, on
the earlier slides I was
writing 1 x -40 and
2104 x 0.25, but
the order doesn't matter, right?
-40 x 1 is the same as 1 x -40.
And this first element, of course,
is "H" applied to 2104.
So it's really the
predicted price of my first house.
Well, how about the second element?
Hope you can see
where I am going to get the second element.
Right?
I'm gonna take this and multiply it by my vector.
And so that's gonna be
-40 x 1 + 0.25 x 1416.
And so this is going be "H" of 1416.
Right?
And so on for the
third and the fourth
elements of this 4 x 1 vector.
And just there, right?
This thing here that I
just drew the green box around,
that's a real number, OK?
That's a single real number,
and this thing here that
I drew the magenta box around--the
purple, magenta color box
around--that's a real number, right?
And so this thing on
the right--this thing on the
right overall, this is a
4 by 1 dimensional matrix, was a 4 dimensional vector.
And, the neat thing about
this is that when you're
actually implementing this in software--so
when you have four houses and
when you want to use your hypothesis
to predict the prices, predict the price "Y" of all of these four houses.
What this means is that, you
know, you can write this in one line of code.
When we talk about octave and
program languages later, you can
actually, you'll actually write this in one line of code.
You write prediction equals my,
you know, data matrix times
parameters, right?
Where data matrix is
this thing here, and parameters
is this thing here, and this
times is a matrix vector multiplication.
And if you just do this then
this variable prediction - sorry
for my bad handwriting - then
just implement this one
line of code assuming you have
an appropriate library to do matrix vector multiplication.
If you just do this,
then prediction becomes this
4 by 1 dimensional vector, on
the right, that just gives you all the predicted prices.
And your alternative to doing
this as a matrix vector multiplication
would be to write eomething like
, you know, for I equals 1 to 4, right?
And you have say a thousand houses
it would be for I equals 1 to a thousand or whatever.
And then you have to write a
prediction, you know, if I equals.
and then do a bunch
more work over there and it
turns out that When you
have a large number of houses,
if you're trying to predict the prices
of not just four but maybe
of a thousand houses then
it turns out that when
you implement this in the
computer, implementing it like this, in any of the various languages.
This is not only true for
Octave, but for Supra Server
Java or Python, other high-level, other languages as well.
It turns out, that, by writing
code in this style on the
left, it allows you to
not only simplify the
code, because, now, you're just
writing one line of code
rather than the form of a bunch of things inside.
But, for subtle reasons, that we
will see later, it turns
out to be much more computationally
efficient to make predictions
on all of the prices of
all of your houses doing it
the way on the left than the
way on the right than if you were to write your own formula.
I'll say more about this
later when we talk about
vectorization, but, so, by
posing a prediction this way, you
get not only a simpler piece
of code, but a more efficient one.
So, that's it for
matrix vector multiplication and we'll
make good use of these sorts
of operations as we develop
the living regression in other models further.
But, in the next video we're
going to take this and generalize this
to the case of matrix matrix multiplication.