In the previous video, we talked
about the form of the
hypothesis for linear regression
with multiple features or with multiple variables.
In this video, let's talk about
how to fit the parameters of that hypothesis.
In particular, how to
use gradient descent for linear
regression with multiple features.
To quickly summarize our notation, this
is our formal hypothesis in multivariate
linear regression where we've
adopted the convention that x zero equals one.
The parameters of this model
are theta zero through theta
n, but instead of
thinking of this as n
separate parameters, which is
valued, I'm instead going to think
of parameters as theta where
theta here is a n+1 dimensional vector.
So I'm just going to think of the parameter.
The parameters of this
model as itself being a vector.
A cost function as J of theta it's zero through theta.
And it's given by this usual subscript.
Instead of thinking of
J as a function
of these and plus one number,
so I'm going to more
commonly write J as just
a function of the parameter
vector theta so that theta here is a vector.
Here's what gradient descent looks like.
We're going to repeatedly update each
parameter theta J according to
theta J minus alpha times this derivative term.
And once again we write
this as J of theta,
so theta J is updated
as theta J minus the learning
rate alpha times the derivative,
a partial derivative of the
cost function with respect to
the parameter theta J. Let's
see what this looks like when
we implement gradient descent and
in particular, let's go see
what that partial derivative looks like.
Here's what we have previously for
gradient descent for when we have
only one feature when N equals one.
We had two separate update rules
for the two parameters theta zero
and theta one and we
will update theta zero according
to this equation on top,
where this term here is
the partial derivative of the
cost function with respect to
the parameter of theta zero
and some of them, we had
an update room for
theta one and when we
had only one feature, we
used to write XI for
a one feature now of
course we call this feature
X subscript one, if we only had one feature.
So that was the old algorithm for the case of one feature.
Let's take a look at gradient
descent for when the number
of features n may be
much larger than one.
Here's what we have for gradient
descent and for the case of
when we had N equals one feature.
We had two separate update rules
for the parameters theta zero
and theta one and hopefully, these
look familiar to you and
this term here was of
course, the partial derivative
of the cost function with respect
to the parameter of theta 0
and similarly, we had a
different update rule for the parameter of theta 1.
There's a one-rule difference
which is and when we previously
had only one feature, we
would call that feature X I,
but now in our new
notation we will of course
call this X superscript I
subscript one to denote our one feature.
So that was for only one feature.
Let's look at the new algorithm
for we have more than one
feature when the number of
features N may be much larger
than one.
We get this update rule for gradient descent and
maybe for those of you that
know calculus, if you take
the definition of the cost function
and take the partial derivative of
the cost function J with respect
to the parameter theta J,
you find that that partial derivative
is exactly that term that
I've just drawn the blue box
around, and if you
implement this you will get
a working implementation of gradient
descent for multivariate regression.
The last thing I'm gonna do
on the slide is give you
a sense of why
some new and old
algorithms are, you know,
sort of the same thing or why they're
both similar algorithms and
why they're both gradient descent algorithms.
Let's consider a case where we
have two features, or maybe
more than two features so we
have three update rules for
the parameters theta zero, theta
one, theta two, and maybe other values of theta as well.
If you look at the update rule
for theta zero, what you
find is that this update
rule here is the
same as the update rule
that we had previously for the case N equals one.
And the reason that they are
equivalent is of course
because in our notational convention
we had this X0 equals
1 convention, which is
why these two terms that I have drawn
magenta boxes around are equivalent.
Similarly, if you look at
the rule for theta one, you
find that this term here
is equivalent to the
term we previously had or
the equation, the update where
we previously had for theta
1 where of course, we're
just, you know, using this new
notation x subscript 1
to denote our new
notation for denoting the first
feature and now that
we have more than one feature,
we can have similar update
rules for the other
parameters like theta two and so on.
There's a lot going
on the slide, so I
definitely encourage you if you
need to, to pause the video and
look at all the math and the
slide slowly to make sure
you understand everything that's going
on here, but if you
implement the algorithm that
in written up here then
you have a working implementation
of linear regression with multiple features.