In this video, I want to
talk about the normal equation and non-invertibility.
This is a somewhat more
advanced concept but there
is something to often been asked
about and, so, I want to talk about here, and answer it here.
But, this is a somewhat more
advanced concept, so, feel free
to consider this optional material
and There's a phenomenon that
you may have run into that
may be, somewhat useful to understand.
But, even if you don't understand it,
the normal equation and linear
regression, you should be able to get that to work okay.
Here's the issue.
For those of you that are,
maybe, some are more familiar with
linear algebra, what some
students were asking me it
is while computing this, theta
goes extras cosx plus
extras of cosy, one of them
matrix X transpose X is non-invertible.
So, for those of
you that know a bit more linear
algebra, you may know
that, you know, only some
matrices are invertible and
some matrices do not have an inverse.
We call those non-invertible matrixes, singular
or degenerate matrixes.
The issue or the problem
if X transpose X being
non invertible, should happen pretty rarely.
And, in octave, if
you implement this to compute
data, it turns out
that this would actually do
the right thing, I am getting
a little technical now,
and I don't want to
go in details, but octave has
two functions for inverting matrices.
One is called p (n) and
the other is called n.  And,
the differences between these two are somewhat technical.
One is the pseudo inverse one
is called the inverse that you
can show mathematically that
use the p (n) function then
this world, this world can
actually compute the value of
data that you want even if X transverse X is noninvertable.
The specific details between, you
know, what is the difference between P
(n) and what is N that's
somewhat advanced hence the
miracle of computing concepts, I don't really want to get into.
But, I thought in this
optional video I'll give, I'll
try to give you a little bit of
intuition about what it
means well, extras of x
is not invertible, those of
you that know more
linear might be interested,
I'm not going to prove this
mathematically but if X transpose X is non-invertible.
There are usually two most
common causes for this.
The first cause is if somehow,
in your learning problem, you have redundant features.
Concretely, when you're trying
to predict housing prices, and
if X1 is the size of
the housing feet, in square
feet, and X2 is the
size of the house in square
meters, then, you know,
one meter is equal to
3.28 feet, rounded to 2 decimals.
And so your two features will
always satisfy the constraint that x1 equals
3.28 square times x2.
And you can show, for
those of you that are just somewhat advanced in the algebra now.
But, if you're inexperienced in the algebra,
you can actually show that if
your two features are related for
a linear equation like this then
matrix X transverse X will be non-invertable.
The second thing that can
cause X transverse X to be non-invertable
is if you're training if
you're trying to run a
learning algorithm with a lot
of features, concretely if M
is less than or equal
to N. For example, if
you imagine that you have
M10 training examples, that
you have N100 features, then
you're trying to fit a parameter
vector theta--which is N+1
dimensional,so it's 101 dimensional--we're trying
to fit 101 parameters from just ten training examples.
And this turns out
to sometimes work, but to not always be a good idea.
Because, as we'll see later,
you might not have enough data,
if you have only 10 examples, to
fit 100 or 101 parameters.
We'll see later in this course
why this might be too
many data to fit this many parameters.
But commonly, what we
do then, if M is
less than N, is to see
if we can either delete
some features or to use
a technique called regularization, which is
something that we'll talk
about later in this course as
well, that will kind of
let you fit in all
the parameters, use a lot
of features, even if you
have a relatively small training set.
But, this, this regularization will be a later topic in this course.
But to summarize, if ever
you find that x transfers
x is singular, or alternatively
find there is non-invertible, what I
recommend you do is first
look at your features and see
if you have redundant features, like
this X1 X2, you know,
being linearly dependent, or
being a linear function of each other like so.
And, if you do have redundant
features and if you just, you know, delete one of these features.
You really don't need both of these features.
If you just delete one of
these features, that would solve
your non-invertibility problem and,
so I will first think
through my features and check if any are redundant.
And if so, then you know,
keep deleting redundant features until they are no longer redundant.
And if your features are
not redundant, I would check if I might have too many features.
And if that's the case, I
would either delete some features
if I can bare to use
fewer features or else
I would consider using regularization, which
is this topic that we will talk about later.
So, that's it for the
normal equation and now
what it means for, if the
matrix X transfers X is non-invertible.
But this is a problem that
you should run, that hopefully you run into pretty rarely.
And, if you just implement it in
octave using P in, using
the P in function, which is
called a pseudo-inverse function.
So we use a different linear
algebra ID, called a pseudo-inverse.
But that implementation should just
do the right thing, even if X transfers X is non-invertible.
Which should happen pretty rarely anyway,
so should not be
a problem for most implementations of linear regression.