In this video, I'd like to
convey to you, the main intuitions
behind how regularization works.
And, we'll also write down
the cost function that we'll use, when we were using regularization.
With the hand drawn examples that
we have on these slides, I
think I'll be able to convey part of the intuition.
But, an even better
way to see for yourself, how
regularization works, is if
you implement it, and, see it work for yourself.
And, if you do the
appropriate exercises after this,
you get the chance
to self see regularization in action for yourself.
So, here is the intuition.
In the previous video, we saw
that, if we were to fit
a quadratic function to this
data, it gives us a pretty good fit to the data.
Whereas, if we were to
fit an overly high order
degree polynomial, we end
up with a curve that may fit
the training set very well, but,
really not be a,
but overfit the data
poorly, and, not generalize well.
Consider the following, suppose we
were to penalize, and, make
the parameters theta 3 and theta 4 really small.
Here's what I
mean, here is our optimization
objective, or here is our
optimization problem, where we minimize
our usual squared error cause function.
Let's say I take this objective
and modify it and add
to it, plus 1000 theta
3 squared, plus 1000 theta 4 squared.
1000 I am just writing down as some huge number.
Now, if we were to
minimize this function, the
only way to make this
new cost function small is
if theta 3 and data
4 are small, right?
Because otherwise, if you have
a thousand times theta 3, this
new cost functions gonna be big.
So when we minimize this
new function we are going
to end up with theta 3
close to 0 and theta
4 close to 0, and as
if we're getting rid
of these two terms over there.
And if we do that, well then,
if theta 3 and theta 4
close to 0 then we are
being left with a quadratic function,
and, so, we end up with
a fit to the data, that's, you know, quadratic
function plus maybe, tiny
contributions from small terms,
theta 3, theta 4, that they may be very close to 0.
And, so, we end up with
essentially, a quadratic function, which is good.
Because this is a
much better hypothesis.
In this particular example, we looked at the effect
of penalizing two of
the parameter values being large.
More generally, here is the idea behind regularization.
The idea is that, if we
have small values for the
parameters, then, having
small values for the parameters,
will somehow, will usually correspond
to having a simpler hypothesis.
So, for our last example, we
penalize just theta 3 and
theta 4 and when both
of these were close to zero,
we wound up with a much simpler
hypothesis that was essentially a quadratic function.
But more broadly, if we penalize all
the parameters usually that, we
can think of that, as trying
to give us a simpler hypothesis
as well because when, you
know, these parameters are
as close as you in this
example, that gave us a quadratic function.
But more generally, it is
possible to show that having
smaller values of the parameters
corresponds to usually smoother
functions as well for the simpler.
And which are therefore, also, less prone to overfitting.
I realize that the reasoning for
why having all the parameters be small.
Why that corresponds to a simpler
hypothesis; I realize that
reasoning may not be entirely clear to you right now.
And it is kind of hard
to explain unless you implement
yourself and see it for yourself.
But I hope that the example of
having theta 3 and theta
4 be small and how
that gave us a simpler
hypothesis, I hope that
helps explain why, at least give
some intuition as to why this might be true.
Lets look at the specific example.
For housing price prediction we
may have our hundred features
that we talked about where may
be x1 is the size, x2
is the number of bedrooms, x3
is the number of floors and so on.
And we may we may have a hundred features.
And unlike the polynomial
example, we don't know, right,
we don't know that theta 3,
theta 4, are the high order polynomial terms.
So, if we have just a
bag, if we have just a
set of a hundred features, it's hard
to pick in advance which are
the ones that are less likely to be relevant.
So we have a hundred or a hundred one parameters.
And we don't know which
ones to pick, we
don't know which
parameters to try to pick, to try to shrink.
So, in regularization, what we're
going to do, is take our
cost function, here's my cost function for linear regression.
And what I'm going to do
is, modify this cost
function to shrink all
of my parameters, because, you know,
I don't know which
one or two to try to shrink.
So I am going to modify my
cost function to add a term at the end.
Like so we have square brackets here as well.
When I add an extra
regularization term at the
end to shrink every
single parameter and so
this
term we tend to shrink
all of my parameters theta 1,
theta 2, theta 3 up
to theta 100.
By the way, by convention the summation
here starts from one so I
am not actually going penalize theta
zero being large.
That sort of the convention that,
the sum I equals one through
N, rather than I equals zero
through N. But in practice,
it makes very little difference, and,
whether you include, you know,
theta zero or not, in
practice, make very little difference to the results.
But by convention, usually, we regularize
only theta  through theta
100. Writing down
our regularized optimization objective,
our regularized cost function again.
Here it is. Here's J of
theta where, this term
on the right is a regularization
term and londer
here is called the regularization parameter and
what londer does, is it
controls a trade off
between two different goals.
The first goal, capture it
by the first goal objective, is
that we would like to train,
is that we would like to fit the training data well.
We would like to fit the training set well.
And the second goal is,
we want to keep the parameters
small, and that's captured by
the second term, by the regularization objective. And by the regularization term.
And what londer, the regularization
parameter does is the controls the trade of
between these two
goals, between the goal of fitting the training set well
and the
goal of keeping the parameter plan
small and therefore keeping the hypothesis relatively
simple to avoid overfitting.
For our housing price prediction
example, whereas, previously, if
we had fit a very high
order polynomial, we may
have wound up with a very,
sort of wiggly or curvy function like
this. If you still fit a high order polynomial
with all the polynomial
features in there, but instead,
you just make sure, to use
this sole of regularized objective, then what
you can get out is in
fact a curve that isn't
quite a quadratic function, but is
much smoother and much simpler
and maybe a curve like the magenta
line that, you know, gives a
much better hypothesis for this data.
Once again, I realize
it can be a bit difficult to see why strengthening the
parameters can have
this effect, but if you
implement yourselves with regularization
you will be able to see
this effect firsthand.
In regularized linear regression, if
the regularization parameter monitor
is set to be very large,
then what will happen is
we will end up penalizing the
parameters theta 1, theta
2, theta 3, theta
4 very highly.
That is, if our hypothesis is this is one down at the bottom.
And if we end up penalizing
theta 1, theta 2, theta
3, theta 4 very heavily, then we
end up with all of these parameters close to zero, right?
Theta 1 will be close to zero; theta 2 will be close to zero.
Theta three and theta four
will end up being close to zero.
And if we do that, it's as
if we're getting rid of these
terms in the hypothesis so that
we're just left with a hypothesis
that will say that.
It says that, well, housing
prices are equal to theta zero,
and that is akin to fitting
a flat horizontal straight line to the data.
And this is an
example of underfitting, and
in particular this hypothesis, this
straight line it just fails
to fit the training set
well. It's just a fat straight
line, it doesn't go, you know, go near.
It doesn't go anywhere near most of the training examples.
And another way of saying this
is that this hypothesis has
too strong a preconception or
too high bias that housing
prices are just equal
to theta zero, and despite
the clear data to the contrary,
you know chooses to fit a sort
of, flat line, just a
flat horizontal line. I didn't draw that very well.
This just a horizontal flat line
to the data. So for
regularization to work well, some
care should be taken,
to choose a good choice for
the regularization parameter londer as well.
And when we talk about multi-selection
later in this course, we'll talk
about a way, a variety
of ways for automatically choosing
the regularization parameter londer as well. So, that's
the idea of the high regularization
and the cost function reviews in
order to use regularization In the
next two videos, lets take
these ideas and apply them
to linear regression and to
logistic regression, so that
we can then get them to
avoid overfitting.