In this video, I would
like to talk about how to
evaluate a hypothesis that has been learned by your algorithm.
In later videos, we will build on this to talk about
how to prevent in the
problems of overfitting
and underfitting as well.
When we fit the parameters of
our learning algorithm we think about
choosing the parameters to minimize the training error.
One might think that getting a
really low value of training error might be a
good thing, but we have
already seen that just because
a hypothesis has low
training error, that doesn't mean it is necessarily a good hypothesis.
And we've already seen the example
of how a hypothesis can overfit.
And therefore fail to generalize
the new examples not in the training set.
So how do you tell if the hypothesis might be overfitting.
In this simple example we could
plot the hypothesis h of
x and just see what was going on.
But in general for problems with
more features than just one
feature, for problems with a
large number of features like these
it becomes hard or may
be impossible to plot what
the hypothesis looks like
and so we need some other way to evaluate our hypothesis.
The standard way to evaluate
a learned hypothesis is as follows.
Suppose we have a data set like this.
Here I have just shown 10
training examples, but of course usually we may have
dozens or hundreds or maybe thousands of training examples.
In order to make sure we
can evaluate our hypothesis, what
we are going to do is split
the data we have into two portions.
The first portion is
going to be our usual
training set and the
second portion is going to
be our test set,
and a pretty typical split of
all the data we have into a
training set and test set
might be around say a 70%,
30% split.
Worth more today to grade
the training set and relatively less to the test set.
And so now, if
we have some data set, we
run a sine of say
70% of the data
to be our training set where
here "m" is as usual
our number of training examples and
the remainder of our data
might then be assigned to become our test set.
And here, I'm going to use
the notation m subscript test
to denote the number of test examples.
And so in general, this
subscript test is going
to denote examples that come
from a test set so that
x1 subscript test, y1 subscript
test is my first
test example which I guess
in this example might be this example over here.
So a fairly typical procedure
for training and testing a
learning algorithm, maybe linear regression,
would be to first learn the
parameter vector from the training data.
And here the training data is only
that first 70% of the dataset.
Finally, one last detail
whereas here I've drawn this
as though the first 70% goes
to the training set and
the last 30% to the test set.
If there is any sort of ordinary to the data.
That should be better to send
a random 70% of
your data to the training set
and a random 30% of your data to the test set.
So if your data were
already randomly sorted, you could
just take the first 70% and
last 30%  that if
your data were not randomly ordered,
it would be better to
randomly shuffle or to
randomly reorder the examples in your training set.
Before you know sending the
first 70% in the
training set and the last
30% of the test set.
Here then is a fairly typical
procedure for how you
would train and test the
learning algorithm and the learning regression.
First, you learn the
parameters theta from the
training set so you minimize
the usual training error objective j of
theta, where j of theta
here was defined using that
70% of all the data you have.
There is only the training data.
And then you would compute the test error.
And I am going to denote the test
error as j subscript test.
And so what you do is
take your parameter theta that
you have learned from the training
set, and plug it in
here and compute your test set error.
Which I am going to write as follows.
So this is basically the average
squared error as measured on your test set.
It's pretty much what you'd expect.
So if we run every test
example through your hypothesis
with parameter theta and just measure
the error
that your hypothesis has on your
m subscript test, test examples.
And of course, this is the
definition of the test set
error if we are using
linear regression and using
the squared error metric.
How about if we were doing a classification problem
and say using logistic regression instead. In that
case, the procedure for training
and testing say logistic regression is pretty similar
first we will do the parameters
from the training data, that first 70% of the data.
And it will compute the test error as follows.
It's the same objective function
as we always use but we
just leave a ration, except
that now is define using our
m subscript test, test examples.
While this definition of the
test set error test is perfectly reasonable.
Sometimes there is an alternative
test sets metric that might
be easier to interpret, and that's the misclassification error.
It's also called the
zero one misclassification error, with
zero one denoting that you
either get an example right or you get an example wrong.
Here's what I mean.
Let me define the error of a prediction.
That is h of x. And
given the label y as equal to
one if my hypothesis
outputs the value greater than
equal to five and Y
is equal to zero or if
my hypothesis outputs a value
of less than 0.5 and y is
equal to one, right, so
both of these cases basic respond
to if your hypothesis mislabeled
the example assuming your threshold at an 0.5.
So either thought it was more
likely to be 1, but
it was actually 0, or your
hypothesis stored
was more likely to be
0, but the label was actually 1.
And otherwise, we define this error function to be zero.
If your hypothesis
basically classified the example y correctly.
We could then define the
test error, using the
misclassification error metric to
be one of
the m tests of sum from
i equals one to m
subscript test of the
error of h of
x(i) test comma y(i).
And so that's
just my way of
writing out that this is
exactly the fraction of
the examples in my test
set that my hypothesis has mislabeled.
And so that's the definition of
the test set error using the
misclassification error of the
0, 1 misclassification metric. So that's
the standard technique for evaluating
how good a learned hypothesis is.
In the next video, we will
adapt these ideas to helping us
do things like choose what features like the
degree polynomial to use
with the learning algorithm or choose
the regularization parameter for learning algorithm.