Sometime people talk about support
vector machines,as large margin
classifiers,in this video I'd
like to tell you what that
means, and this will
also give us a useful
picture of what an
hypothesis may look like.
Here's my Cos function for the support
vector machine where here on the left
I've plotted my Cos 1
of z function that I used for positive examples and on the right I've  plotted my
zero of 'Z' function graph
here, with 'Z' on the horizontal axis.
Now, let's think about what
it takes to these cos functions small.
If you have a positive example,
so if y is equal to
1, then cos 1 of
Z is zero only when
Z is greater than or equal to 1.
So in other words, if you
have a positive example, we really
want theta [xx] to be greater
than or equal to 1
and conversely if y is
equal to zero, of this
cos zero of z function,
then it's only in
this region that z is
less than equal to 1
we have the course is zero
as z is equals to zero,
and this is an interesting property of the support
vector machine right, which is
that, if you have positive
example so if y is equal to one,
then all we really need
is that data transport is greater than equal zero.
And that would mean we classify correctly
because if theta [xx] x is greater than zero our
hypothesis will predict zero.
And similarly, if you have
a negative example, they
less than zero and that will make sure we get the example right.
But the support machine wants to do more than that.
It says, you don't just barely get the example right.
So then don't just
have it just a little bit bigger thans zero. What
i really want to is for
this to be quite a lot
because its zero, say maybe
quick printed and you can
and I want this to be much less than zero.
Maybe I want it less than or
equal to -1.
And so this builds in an
extra safety factor or safety
margin factor the support vector
machine logstic regressions
are something similar too of
course but lets see what
happens or lets see what
comes consequences of this are, in the
context of the support vector machine.
Concretely, what we'd like
to do next is consider a
case where we set
this constant C to be
a very large value, so let's
imagine we shall see through
a very large value, may be a hundred thousand, some huge number.
Lets see what the support vector machine will do.
If C is very,
very large, then when minimizing
this optimization objective, we're going
to be highly motivated to choose
a value, so that this
first term is equal to zero.
So let's try to
understand the optimization problem in
the context of, what would
it take to make this
first term in the objective
equal to zero, because you
know, maybe we'll set C to
some huge constant, and this
will hope, this should give us
additional intuition about what
sort of hypotheses a support vector machine learns.
So we saw already that
whenever you have a training
example with a label
of y1 if you
want to make that first term
zero, what you need is
is to find a value of theta
so that theta is greater
than or equal to 1.
Whenever we have an example,
we label zero in order
to make sure that the cost
cause zero of Z,  in order to
make sure that the cost cause
zero we need that theta transfer
was xy is less than or
equal to, minus one?
So, if we think
of our optimization problem as
now, really choosing parameters
and showing that this first
term is equal to zero,
what we're left with is
the following optimization problem, we're
going to minimize that first
term zero, so if C
times zero, because we're going
to choose parameters so that's equal
to zero, plus one half
and then you know that
second term and this
first term is 'C' times zero,
so let's just cross that
out because I know that's going to be zero.
And this will be subject to the constraint
that theta transpose xi
is greater than or equal to
one, if yi
Is equal to one and
the xi is less than
or equal to minus one
whenever you have
a negative example and it
turns out that when you
solve this authorization problem it
minimize this as a function of the parameters date
you get a very interesting decision
boundary. Concretely if you
look at a data set
like this with positive and negative examples,  this data
is linearly separable and by
that I mean that there exists s straight line,
there is as many straight rate
on it as they can separate the positive
the good example
is perfectly. For example, here is one discussion boundary
that separates the positive and
negative example, but somehow that
doesn't look like a very
natural one, right or by
drawing even worse you know
here's another decision boundary that
separates the positive and negative examples  and I'll
give examples we'll just be
having but neither of those seem like categorical choices.
The Support Vector Machines will instead choose this
decision boundary, whichI'm drawing in black.
And that seems like a much better.
boundary then either of
the one's that I drew in magenta or in green.
The black line seems like a more
robust separator, it does
a better job of separating the
positive and negative example and mathematically,
what that does is, this
boundary has a larger distance.
That distance is called the margin, when I
draw up this two extra
blue lines, we see
that the black decision boundary has
some larger minimum distance from any of my.
The good example is we
are extra momentary the green
lines thick humble thick close
to the training example that seems
to do a less great job separating the positive and negative classes than my black line.
And so
this distance is called
the margin of the
support fax machine and this
gives the SVM a certain
robustness, because it tries
to separate the data with as
a large a margin as possible.
So the support vector machine is
sometimes also called a large
margin classifier and this
is actually a consequence of
the optimization problem we wrote down on the previous one.
I know that you might be
wondering how is it that
the optimization problem I wrote
down in the previous while, how
does that lead to this large margin classifier.
I know I haven't explained that yet.
And in the next video
I'm going to sketch a
little bit of the intuition about why
that optimization problem gives us
this large margin classifier, but
this is a useful feature to
keep in mind if you are
trying to understand what are the
source of hypothesis that the Nesbian will choose.
That is, trying to separate the
positive and negative examples with as big a margin as possible.
Once you say one last thing
about large margin classifier in
this intuition, so we
left out this large margin classification
setting in the case
of when C organization concepts
was very large, I think
they say that's a hundred thousand something.
So give a dataset
like this, maybe we'll choose
that decision boundary that
separate the possible examples of large margins.
Now, DSDM is actually sliding
more sophisticated than this large
margin view might suggest
and in particular all you're
doing is use a large
margin classifier then your
learning algorithms can be sensitive
to out liners, so lets just
add an extra your positive example
like that shown on the screen.
If he had one example then
it seems as that the separate
data with a large margin,
maybe I'll end up learning
the decision boundary like that
right by this little gentle line and
it's really not clear that based
on the single outlier based on
a single example and it's
really not clear that it's
actually a good idea to change
my decision boundary from the black
one over to the magenta one.
So, if C, if
the regularization parameter C were very
large, then this is
actually what DSDM will do, it will
change the discussion boundary
from the black to the
monugental one but if
c is reasonably small if
you were to use the C,
not too large then you
still end up with this
black decision behind you the data were not.
And of course if the data were not linearly separable soo if you had some positive
examples in here, or if
you had some negative examples
in here then the DSDM
will also do the right thing.
And so this picture of
a large margin classifier that's
really, that's really the
picture that is only
for the case of when the
regulations and C is
very large, and just
to remind you this corresponds C
plays a role similar to
one over Lambda when Lambda
is the regularization parameter
we have previously have so it's
only that one of the Lambda
is very large or if
Lambda with is very small that
you end up with things like
this Magenta decision boundary, but
in practice when the applying support vector machines
,when C
is not very, very large like
it can, we want if it can
do a better job ignoring
the few other lines like here. And
it'll fine and  do reasonable things
even if your data is not linearly separable.
But when we talk about buyers and theories in the context of support vector machines
which will do
a little bit later, hopefully all
of you sterols involve the regularization
perimeter will become clearer at
that time. So I hope
that gives some intuition about
how this functions as
a large margin crossfire that
tries to separate the data with
a large margin, technically this
picture of this view is true
only when the parameter C is very large
, which
is a useful way to think about support vector machines.
There was one missing step in
this video which is, why is
it that optimization problem we
wrote down on these
lines, how does that actually
lead to the large margin classifier, I
didn't do that in this video,
in the next video I
will sketch a little bit
more of the man behind that
to explain
that separate reasoning of how
the optimization problem we wrote out
results in a large margin classifier.